<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Earthquakes on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</title>
    <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/tags/earthquakes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Earthquakes on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2020 Pablo J. González</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/tags/earthquakes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>UK NERC-COMET</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/project/2014-2021_comet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/project/2014-2021_comet/</guid>
      <description>The Centre for Observation and Modelling of Earthquakes, Volcanoes and Tectonics (COMET) uses satellite measurements alongside ground-based observations and geophysical models to study earthquakes and volcanoes, and help understand the hazards they pose.
A national-scale community with considerable size and impact, COMET brings together world-leading scientists across the British Geological Survey (BGS) and 10 UK universities: Bristol, Cambridge, Durham, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester, Newcastle, Oxford, Reading and UCL. We work closely with the Natural Environment Research Council (NERC), National Centre for Earth Observation (NCEO) and European Space Agency (ESA), as well as many other national and international partners.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hawai&#39;i 2012 a trip to live geohazards: Earthquake, Tsunami, and Volcanoes</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121104_hawaii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121104_hawaii/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I have visited the Maui and Big Island in Hawai’i. I must admit I haven’t had the time to visit Maui properly due to a busy conference schedule ACES2012, so I hope to have another chance to explore the plenty nice rain-forests and waterfalls (Road to Hana), the Haleakala volcano, or just surfing the eastern coast outer reefs (my other passion in life).
However, as I landed into the Big Island, my first passion in life the natural hazards become so intense that I don’t regret to pass the opportunity to surf in Hawai’i (something that certainly sounds very cool to my folks back in the Canary Islands).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2011 Lorca earthquake: groundwater unloading of the crust</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121019_lorca/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121019_lorca/</guid>
      <description>As recent as Monday, a group of colleagues and myself published a paper in Nature Geoscience, showing proof of a positive correlation between the slip distribution occurred during the 2011 Lorca earthquake and the mid-term (50-years) stress changes due to a crustal unloading groundwater mass removal process. This finding is quite exciting, hitting the media and apparently causing lot of discussion. However, I regret to see some news reports highlighting the word &amp;ldquo;caused&amp;rdquo;, something we didn&amp;rsquo;t say nor endorse in our study.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>