<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Volcano and Fault Mechanics on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</title>
    <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Volcano and Fault Mechanics on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2020 Pablo J. González</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>COMPACT</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/project/2020-2022_compact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/project/2020-2022_compact/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project “Remote Characterization of groundwater storage changes using geophysical Observations and Modelling of Poroelastic processes in Aquifers, under Compaction and Transient groundwater flow conditions” (COMPACT - PID2019-104571RA-I00) aims to develop new methods to estimate groundwater storage changes in aquifers using non-invasive geophysical methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, it is estimated that over 2 billion people rely on groundwater as their dominant water supply source. Our dependence will increase due to growing demand and climate change limiting access to surface waters.
Aquifer systems are porous and permeable systems that store water. Groundwater systems respond to natural and anthropogenic recharge and discharge fluxes by changes in water storage and fluid pore-pressure (head), affecting complex fluid flow. Monitoring and understanding of the changes in groundwater storage is essential to manage this vital natural resource.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, estimating groundwater resource changes, at smaller scale (&amp;lt;10km), is notoriously difficult and improvements are needed. Traditional methods involve limited data (e.g., costly phreatic level monitoring wells) and a complex physical modeling process, with large uncertainties due to high heterogeneity in aquifer systems. Alternatively, geodetic and geophysical methods can provide useful constrains. Surface displacements can track fluid pore-pressure change in shallow compacting aquifers, and gravity can provide key information of mass-changes. Therefore, we are limited on the type of aquifers and spatial resolution, at an affordable cost, on which we can estimate groundwater resource changes with non-invasive geophysical measurements. We need new physical constrains to estimate aquifer groundwater storage changes in any type of aquifer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will overcome past limitations by implementing the necessary experimental and theoretical understanding to estimate groundwater storage changes using non-invasive surface geophysical measurements. We will establish the quantitative relationships to physically model storage change using variations in seismic ambient wavefield (natural occurring ground vibrations). We will use gravity and surface displacements, along with the necessary physical and mechanical rock sample laboratory experiments to separate 1) the effects of time-dependent aquifer internal deformation (compaction), 2) fluid flow in the aquifer non-saturated zone, from 3) the actual water content change. We will use the exceptional hydrogeological conditions of the Tenerife Island, to record seismic ambient wavefield, to confirm our predictions and calibrate our models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project addresses important questions in groundwater resource management; and will contribute to our understanding of how to use geophysical signals can illuminate groundwater dynamics. This will, in turn, improve monitoring and detection changes in aquifer systems. The feasibility of using geophysical (gravity, seismic and surface displacements) as a continuous, passive, non-invasive, remote tool to detect and characterize groundwater storage changes will be scrupulously evaluated. We anticipate that our research will influence the development of new strategies to monitor and forecast groundwater natural resources in near real-time and high-spatiotemporal resolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want more information, please visit our &lt;a href=&#34;https://proyectocompact.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dr Pablo J Gonzalez</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/pablojgonzalez/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/pablojgonzalez/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I grew up in Tenerife loving seawater and mountain views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I was told that Teide was a volcano. Few solar revolutions later, a high-school geology teacher inspired me to spend more time looking at rocks. So I did, and at 18, I left Tenerife to Granada and I met more inspiring teachers. There, they call them, professors (thanks Juan Ignacio Soto and Jose Morales). Before graduate, I had a great summer at a Mexican volcano and a full year in Germany (thanks Janet). There, a wise old German man showed me to download wiggles caused by far-away ruptures (thanks Rainer Kind). I ignored much about how big a deal were GFZ Potsdam and its on-line library, but it allowed me to discover some intriguing and hypnotic multicolour images from Iceland. Back in Spain, GPS became my first paid job, but laud bosses darken my soul. I chose to go alone and watched multicolour images to cheer me up. I escaped to Canada, met good friends and had bad times. Back to Europe, I had more bad times, but it was improving. I was improving. One day, someone told me that what I do was really good at the right time. So I must always thank him to allow me call Liverpool home. 20 years passed since I left the seawater and mountain views. I was happier than ever, and I thought that I could even be bold. So, thanks to everyone on the road…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2019, I am a volcanologist who enjoys seawater and mountain views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-interets&#34;&gt;Research Interets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volcano geodesy and magmatic processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earthquakes and fault mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lithosphere dynamics and structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rock and fluid interactions due to natural and anthropogenic processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ph.D., Geodesy and Geophysics, University Complutense Madrid, Madrid, Spain (2010)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M.Sc., Geodetic and Cartographic Engineering, University Complutense Madrid, Madrid, Spain (2006)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;B.Sc., Geological Sciences, University of Granada, Granada, Spain (2003)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;professional-experience&#34;&gt;Professional Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2019- Senior Researcher, IPNA-CSIC, La Laguna, Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2019 Senior Researcher, IGEO-CSIC, Madrid, Spain (2 months)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016-2019 Lecturer in Geophysics, University of Liverpool, Liverpool, UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2014-2016 Satellite geodesy Research Fellow, University of Leeds, Leeds, UK&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012-2014 Banting Postdoctoral Fellow, Univ. Western Ontario, London, ON, Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010-2012 Postdoctoral Fellow, Univ. Western Ontario, London, ON, Canada&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008 Visiting Research Scientist, INGV-CNT, Rome, Italy (2 months) and INGV-Catania, Italy (3 months)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007 Visiting Research Scientist, Univ. Western Ontario, London, ON, Canada (2 months)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006-2010 Research Fellow, Universidad Computense de Madrid, Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2003-2006 Project Research Scientist (Interreg-ALERTA project), ITER, Tenerife, Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2003 Junior Project Research Scientist, GFZ-Potsdam, Germany (4 months)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002 Visiting Training Student, Colima Volcanological Observatory, Mexico (2 months)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;awards&#34;&gt;Awards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RAS Group achievement Award for Geophysics (Royal Astronomical Society of London), as member of the COMET research group (2018)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Banting Fellow of the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SOEST Young Investigator award, University of Hawaii – Manoa, HI, USA (declined) (2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UCM Predoctoral Research Fellowship (2006)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Past members</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/pastmembers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/pastmembers/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postdoc-researchers&#34;&gt;Postdoc researchers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr &lt;a href=&#34;lbie.weebly.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Lidong Bie&lt;/a&gt; (COMET Postdoctoral researcher), &lt;em&gt;working on earthquake source processes combining seismology and geodesy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;phd-and-mphil-students&#34;&gt;PhD and MPhil students&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr Guadalupe Brú (PhD 2018), research on monitoring landslides. Currently at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tomtom.com/en_gb/navigation/#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;TomTom.com&lt;/a&gt;. Currently a science data analyst at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tomtom.com/es_es/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tom Tom Spain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mr. Teo Nagy (MSc 2018), MPhil Thesis: Automatic glacier displacement maps using Sentinel-2 satellite images. Currently a data analyst at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nve.no/hydrology/glaciers/copernicus-glacier-service/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Norwegian Polar Institute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mr. Jorge Vargas Rivera (MSc Petroleum Geology student, 2016), &lt;em&gt;Induced seismicity at depleting gas reservoirs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;undergraduate-students&#34;&gt;Undergraduate students&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ms. Jennifer Bichard-Collins (BSc Geophysics, 2016) &lt;em&gt;Graben formation at magmatic rifting zones using mechanical numerical modeling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ms. Hannah Gigg (BSc Geophysics, 2016) &lt;em&gt;Mechanics of megathrust events: the 2016 M7.8 Pedernales, Ecuador earthquake&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visitors</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/visitors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/visitors/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;visitors&#34;&gt;Visitors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ms Sara Rodríguez Molina, PhD Student @ IGEO-CSIC, Madrid (May-June 2017), &lt;em&gt;planned work on time-dependent volcano deformation models&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work with us</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/workwithus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/workwithus/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;work-with-us&#34;&gt;Work with us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Liverpool with the Earth, Ocean and Ecological Sciences has a prestigious PhD program in Earth Sciences, all the information on the programme and the requirements to enter are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/earth-ocean-and-ecological-sciences/research/postgraduate-opportunities/earth-and-ocean-sciences/earth-and-ocean-sciences-phd/overview/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are already graduated from a MSc or BSc degree in some discipline in Earth Sciences, I can help you to fund your PhD studies using one of the following funding options:
1. Usually, I offer PhD projects for the Liverpool-Manchester Doctoral Training Programme. There are 12 competitive awards each year, although priority is given to British nationals every nationality is encouraged to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/studentships-earth-atmosphere-ocean/studentships/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;apply&lt;/a&gt;
2. A highly regarded option for any potential student open to any nationality is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/student-administration/research-students/fees-and-funding/scholarships/duncan-norman-research-scholarship/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Duncan Normal Research Scholarship&lt;/a&gt;. This Scholarship is highly competitive, therefore I encourage you to contact me as soon as possible to prepare a high quality application.
3. If you are a Chinese national, there is another independent route for you to come to work with us at Liverpool. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/study/postgraduate/finance/scholarships/china-scholarship/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The University of Liverpool and China Scholarship Council Awards&lt;/a&gt;, is a fully funded scholarship that covers all your research and teaching fees with an allowance for a paid return trip to the UK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In additional, to those routes there could be other opportunities based on specific successful research grants. Therefore, I will also encourage to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:pjgonzal@liverpool.ac.uk&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;contact me&lt;/a&gt; for an update on other possible posts in my group.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Talk</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Embed your slides or video here using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gcushen.github.io/hugo-academic-demo/post/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;. Further details can easily be added using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2016: Surface uplift and time-dependent seismic hazard due to fluid injection in eastern Texas</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/publication/2016/2016-09-26_shirzaeietal_science/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/publication/2016/2016-09-26_shirzaeietal_science/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UK NERC-COMET</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/project/2014-2021_comet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/project/2014-2021_comet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Observation and Modelling of Earthquakes, Volcanoes and Tectonics (COMET) uses satellite measurements alongside ground-based observations and geophysical models to study earthquakes and volcanoes, and help understand the hazards they pose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A national-scale community with considerable size and impact, COMET brings together world-leading scientists across the British Geological Survey (BGS) and 10 UK universities: Bristol, Cambridge, Durham, Leeds, Liverpool, Manchester, Newcastle, Oxford, Reading and UCL. We work closely with the Natural Environment Research Council (NERC), National Centre for Earth Observation (NCEO) and European Space Agency (ESA), as well as many other national and international partners.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observando los volcanoes desde el espacio</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20140712_observandovolcanoesdesdeelespacio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20140712_observandovolcanoesdesdeelespacio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Con una cotidianidad pasmosa nos hemos llegado a acostumbrar a mirar el televisor cada día después de las noticias, y ver una perpectiva, inusual, de otro mundo, uno que nunca hemos observado desde ese punto de vista, pero que sin embargo reconocemos con facilidad. Somos capaces de identificar sin dificultad las líneas continentales, las masas de agua y, el objetivo de esa representación en cámara, la evolución de las nubes, y por ende, del vapor de agua listo para descargar sobre nuestras cabezas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoy en día, la observación de la Tierra desde el espacio es una herramienta fundamental no sólo para la predicción del tiempo meteorológico que vamos a disfrutar o, muy de vez en cuando en Canarias, a sufrir. En la última década, la popularización de Google Earth ha democratizado el uso de las imágenes de teledetección por sátelite, y ya más de uno, no puede imaginar su trabajo laboral o la planificación de sus vacaciones sin esa herramienta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el campo de la volcanología, la observación de la Tierra desde el espacio o teledección ha ido progresando lenta pero de forma segura. Tras la segunda guerra mundial, las superpotencias se lanzaron a desarrollar ambiciosos programas de satélites artificiales para ganar “inteligencia”, básicamente cartografiar el terreno y evaluar los recursos naturales a escala global. Esta carrera de experimentación culminó a principios de los años 70 con el desarrollo del programa civil estadounidense &lt;a href=&#34;http://landsat.gsfc.nasa.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Landsat&lt;/a&gt;, que continua en la actualidad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Los satélites Landsat y decenas de misiones similares orbitan alrededor de La Tierra escaneando repetidamente casi toda la superificie del planeta, con lo que se facilita la detección de cambios del terreno. Estos satélites llevan incorporados sensores muy sofisticados que registran la energía que libera o refleja la superificie terrestre. Esa energía puede ser la energía por radiación calórica de una colada de lava o de una zona de fumarolas, la radiación solar reflejada por el suelo durante el día, etcétera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basándonos en la interpretación cuidadosa de esas interacciones de energía con el terreno somos capaces de detectar cambios de temperatura, de composición de los gases en la  atmósfera, o incluso de la distancia que separa la superficie del volcán con respecto a un satélite. En definitiva, la observación de la Tierra desde el espacio nos permiten obtener observaciones continuas, seguras y fiables, de muy diversos parámetros geométricos y físico-químicos entorno a un volcán.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el caso del volcanismo de las Islas Canarias, no ha sido hasta la introducción de técnicas de observación desde satélite que hemos sido capaces de registrar el comportamiento de toda una  isla a la presión ejercida por el magma en profundidad. Utilizando una técnica denominada interferometría radar, se ha podido comprobar la extensión de los cambios topográficos inducidos por la acumulación del magma antes y durante de la erupción de El Hierro [1]. Una información que difícilmente podría haberse recabado de otra forma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Las observaciones desde el espacio son, por tanto, muy valiosas, aunque no pueden enterderse como un sustituto de la vigilancia volcánica sobre el terreno, sino como un complemento fiable y seguro para la evaluación y seguimiento del nivel de actividad de un volcán.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] González P.J., Samsonov S., Pepe S., Tiampo K.F., Tizzani P., Casu F., Fernández J., Camacho A.G., and Sansosti E. (2013), Magma storage and migration associated with the 2011-2012 El Hierro eruption: Implications for shallow magmatic systems at oceanic island volcanoes, Journal of Geophysical Research – Solid Earth, 118, 4361–4377, doi:&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/jgrb.50289&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10.1002/jgrb.50289&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3D-DEF code and manual/tutorial (.pdf)</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130517_3defcode/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130517_3defcode/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I encountered a ground deformation problem where the slip along a particular &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fault_%28geology%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;fault&lt;/a&gt; seems not partitioned (distributed) as usual. Most of the elastic dislocation codes assume that slip partitions about half of the slip on one side block (hangingwall) and the other half along the other block (footwall), e.g., the popular &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mathworks.com/matlabcentral/fileexchange/25982&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Okada codes&lt;/a&gt;. These codes will not work when slip occurs only due to the motion of one block. This is basically the problem I want to study, for this you need more advance and flexible programs, one of those is 3D-DEF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D-DEF code is a three-dimensional boundary-element model that allows the calculation of stresses, strains, and displacements within and on the surface of an elastic half-space (it means, there is no bottom to the model). The power of the model comes from the ability to a) solve for a variety of deformation quantities on a variety of faults and planes simultaneously, and b) to drive the deformation in relatively realistic (and therefore potentially complex) ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I just downloaded the package few days ago. However, I found that the package you can download from &lt;a href=&#34;https://umdrive.memphis.edu/mellis/public/3ddef.tar&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; will not compile at your first try using default linux-installed gfortran compiler. Some modifications were necessary, which are minimal but related to the length of lines (a constrain of fortran codes). Another problem was the order of compilation of the subprograms, even after correcting this. Compilation will fail due to some preexisting .mod files, producing some errors. So I have worked around those little problems, and I have uploaded a mild corrected version of the package &lt;a href=&#34;data/3ddef.tar.bz2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (well due to restriction on the file extensions in wordpress, it’ll require that you remove the “_removepdfextension.pdf” before uncompress the tarball file). In this package, in addition to the slightly modified code, I have added a simple compile.me script that can be executed and will create the 3d program for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I also typeset the manual from the website in latex to generate the documentation in an amenable and print-able friendly way. There are two documents, the manual and the tutorial. Those documents provide essentially the same information as in the website, but I cannot discard typos during the translation. So, I encourage to visit the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ceri.memphis.edu/people/ellis/3ddef/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;on-line documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope those modifications will be of some help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;data/3ddef-tar-bz2_removepdfextension.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carta Abierta al IGN: Política de acceso a datos científicos</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130401_cartaabiertaign/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130401_cartaabiertaign/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Estimado Sr./Sra.,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikimedia
Wikimedia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me dirijo a Ud. para solicitar que hagan pública su política de acceso a datos científicos generados por el Insituto Geográfico Nacional de España (IGN).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creo que es de interés público, y en particular de aquellos científicos españoles e internacionales interesados en procesos geológicos y geofísicos ocurridos en el territorio español y sus proximidades, saber cuando, bajo qué condiciones, detalles técnicos de adquisición y en qué formato se puede acceder a todos los datos de carácter científico recabados por el IGN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mientras, que muchos datos generados por el IGN de carácter cartográfico, etc, cuentan con servidores públicos de descarga y con licencias de uso diferenciadas y claras (&lt;a href=&#34;http://centrodedescargas.cnig.es/CentroDescargas/index.jsp&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;centro de descargas&lt;/a&gt;). Dentro de su misma institución, el acceso y política sobre datos cientifícos es escasa o ausente, lo que desincentiva su obtención y utilización. El acceso es, en general, discrecional puesto que algunos datos se encuentran accesibles de forma gráfica y/o tabulada mientras que otros, normalmente los datos “brutos” apenas se tiene constancia de su adquisión o almacenamiento.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Este panorama menoscaba la credibilidad del IGN como un ente de investigación, como atestiga su reciente inclusión en el listado de instituciones que pueden solicitar proyectos de investigación de I+D del Progama Nacional del MINECO, así como la calidad de la información que publica. Esta situación contrasta con lo que debería ser su papel de potenciador de actividades que fomenten mejoras científico-técnicas que contribuyan a sus actividades estatutarias (por ejemplo, vigilancia sísmica y volcánica, campo geomagnético,…etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Los datos y productos publicados por las &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ign.es/web/ign/portal/sis-area-sismicidad&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;redes nacionales sísmica&lt;/a&gt; y de &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ign.es/web/ign/portal/vlc-area-volcanologia&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;vigilancia volcánica&lt;/a&gt; (que por su volumen son los más importantes a los que me refiero y que se ha comprobado que atraen la atención pública) deberían de contar con información clara, actualizada y veraz sobre el estado de las redes instrumentales, sus métodos de adquisición y análisis de datos, así como una política clara de acceso a estos datos por parte de terceros. Esto se puede llevar a cabo en forma de diferentes licencias de uso según perfiles de usuarios. Estas licencias deberían ser accesibles de forma plurilingüe (prefentemente en castellano e inglés), y garantizar su acceso universal independendientemente de la nacionalidad y filiciación del solicitante.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Las licencias de uso de datos científicos públicos garantizarían la difusión y reutilización de datos científicos costosos de adquirir y preservar, dotando de argumentos para el mantenimiento y mejora de estas redes que gestiona el IGN frente a los organismos responsables financiadores. La reducción de las barreras de acceso a los datos científicos fomentaría una comunidad científica mucho más competitiva, y por ende contribuir a que sea más competente. Una comunidad científica competitiva estará constantemente interesada en la explotación y el desarrollo de mejoras técnicas. Este ambiente competitivo beneficiaría de forma global a las tareas que el IGN sirve a nuestra sociedad, y a una mejor visibilidad e interés de los fenómenos geológicos y geofísicos ocurridos en España, sobre todo en una sociedad de la información, a la par que atraer el interés de la comunidad  científica internacional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sin otro particular reciba saludos cordiales,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pablo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nota: Por favor, abstengase de preguntarme a que datos científicos en particular quiero tener acceso. Los solicitaré siguiendo los trámites que consideren oportunos (licencias,…etc.), una vez sean de dominio público, se puedan consultar y solicitar a través de su página web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nota 2: Este correo se publicará en forma de carta abierta en mi blog personal &lt;a href=&#34;https://geomechanics.wordpress.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://geomechanics.wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;.
ADENDA EN LA VERSION ON-LINE: Esta carta ha sido enviada el 1 de Abril de 2013 a consulta@cnig.es en respuesta a la sugerencia de la cuenta oficial de twitter &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/IGNSpain&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;@IGNSpain&lt;/a&gt;, a raíz de un &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/IGNSpain/status/318629575842209792%22%3E1%20de%20abril%20de%202013%3C/a%3E%3C/blockquote%3E%20%3Cscript%20async%20src=%22//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js%22%20charset=%22utf-8%22%3E%3C/script%3E&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; que realicé del 31 de Marzo de 2013 a consecuencia de la eliminación de la solución preliminar de momento tensor para un &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.01.ign.es/ign/layoutIn/volcaDetalleTerremotos.do?evid=1202861&amp;amp;zona=2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;terremoto de MbLg 4.9 ocurrido en la isla de El Hierro&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hawai&#39;i 2012 a trip to live geohazards: Earthquake, Tsunami, and Volcanoes</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121104_hawaii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121104_hawaii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I have visited the Maui and Big Island in Hawai’i. I must admit I haven’t had the time to visit Maui properly due to a busy conference schedule &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scec.org/aces2012/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ACES2012&lt;/a&gt;, so I hope to have another chance to explore the plenty nice rain-forests and waterfalls (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hana_Highway&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Road to Hana&lt;/a&gt;), the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haleakal%C4%81&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Haleakala volcano&lt;/a&gt;, or just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q6wasxESGsY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;surfing the eastern coast outer reefs&lt;/a&gt; (my other passion in life).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as I landed into the Big Island, my first passion in life the natural hazards become so intense that I don’t regret to pass the opportunity to surf in Hawai’i (something that certainly sounds very cool to my folks back in the Canary Islands). After spending much of the first day visiting the ancient and eroded &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kohala_%28mountain%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kohala&lt;/a&gt; volcano, where you can find a variety of climatic regions. A volcano with a desert in the west coast, rainforest of the deep ravines of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waipio_Valley&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Waipi’o&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pololu_Valley&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pololu&lt;/a&gt; valleys in the eastern coast and Irish-style grasslands in the eastern mountain-top and Waimea town areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day, I paid attention to a plenty of road signs indicating the areas to be inundated in case of tsunami. Even, I took a picture, because in Spain I never saw a sign like this, despite the risk that some Spanish coasts are prompt to experience a tsunami in the future. As it happened in the past, such as the huge tsunami of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1755_Lisbon_earthquake&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;1755 Lisbon earthquake&lt;/a&gt; that hit much of the North Atlantic coastlines (e.g., Cadiz and Huelva), or the minor tsunami associated to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2003_Boumerd%C3%A8s_earthquake&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;2003 Algerian earthquake&lt;/a&gt; that hit the Balearic Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Kohala volcano tour, I was heading for my hotel in Kailua (Kona district). And I visited the internet to check my flooded email inbox due to the news reports on our Nature Geoscience article. I also checked twitter for any interesting thing, and I read @EricFielding and @CPPGeophysics tweeting about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.earthquakescanada.nrcan.gc.ca/recent_eq/2012/20121028.0304/index-eng.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mw7.7 Haida Guaii Island earthquake&lt;/a&gt;, back in my residence country, Canada. A quite large earthquake but not horrific for damage due to its remoteness. Then, I visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ptwc.weather.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pacific Tsunami Warning Center&lt;/a&gt;, and at that time (~7 pm HST) no warning or advisory was in effect (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pabloj_gonzalez/status/262420807681204224&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweeting about it&lt;/a&gt;). I even had the time to sent an email to a friend to start planning radar satellite images acquisition and processing to detect ground deformations associated to the coseismic slip. Therefore, I went to have dinner being sure that the earthquake was relatively moderate for triggering a large tsunami and there were no official warnings in effect. However, it was right in front of the hotel that a driver yelled “tsunami is coming”, but I said myself “Come on,… you’ve just checked less than five minutes ago”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 7.45-7.50 HST, about 40 minutes later the sirens started to be listening along the coast, fortunately I was walking back to my room, so I accelerated my steps to get into the room, check again the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ptwc.weather.gov/ptwc/?region=2&amp;amp;id=hawaii.TSUHWX.2012.10.28.0514&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Pacific Tsunami Warning Center messages&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/pabloj_gonzalez/status/262437342344777728&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tweeted it&lt;/a&gt; and pack my stuff. It was relatively clear that at least we have ~2 hours before the first waves arrived to the Hawaiian Islands. At the hotel reception, the outstanding staff distributed evacuation routes and noted the people that was leaving (next morning, you could realize that your room door was marked with a green cross, meaning you left, and other rooms have orange crosses). Although it was some thick traffic, it took only 15 min to reach the designated shelter area, the Kealakehe High School. At that moment (Saturday night), the high schools teachers were in a football game in the school’s field, so they acted promptly and very professionally preparing the gym with water, some vending food, and set up a TV to follow the news and authority messages. An hour later, about 50-60 people were gathered in the high school’s gym and parking lot waiting and/or watching the TV. Everything run smoothly, the tsunami waves arrived around 10.40 pm HST with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://mauinow.com/2012/10/28/video-maui-tsunami-aftermath-being-assessed/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;max of 70 cm at Kahului, Maui&lt;/a&gt;. About 2 hours later (1 am HST), the authorities downgraded the warning to advisory level, and we could return to our hotels. At 4 am HST, the advisory was lifted too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, nothing has happened this time, but it is acting like this &lt;strong&gt;taking seriously every time&lt;/strong&gt; and not downplaying the natural hazards, despite some false alarm cases, which will warranty Hawai’i an enjoyable and safe place to visit. In the future, I hope to see in Spain and Portugal, a full tsunami warning system, but at least a first phase could be to set up tsunami inundation evacuation area signs along the coast. Unfortunately, we don’t know when a tsunami could occur, so small, continuous and progressive actions should be taken along most worldwide coastlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you are curious, the rest of my trip was really pleasant enjoying geological beauties, the Mauna Kea, Mauna Loa and Kilauea volcanoes, and the amazing fault systems of Hilina Pali, Koa’e and Kaoiki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caption: Tsunami inundation road sign at Kawaihae, HI. This picture was taken 2012/10/27 around 12.30 pm HST, about 6 hours before the Mw7.7 Hadai Gwaii earthquake, B.C., Canada. Photo: Pablo J. Gonzalez&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caption: Halema’uma’u crater in the Kilauea summit caldera (2012/10/28). Photo: Pablo J. Gonzalez&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caption: Koa’e fault system, Kilauea volcano (2012/10/28). Photo: Pablo J. Gonzalez&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2011 Lorca earthquake: groundwater unloading of the crust</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121019_lorca/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121019_lorca/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As recent as Monday, a group of colleagues and myself published a paper in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/ngeo/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/ngeo1610.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nature Geoscience&lt;/a&gt;, showing proof of a positive correlation between the slip distribution occurred during the 2011 Lorca earthquake and the mid-term (50-years) stress changes due to a crustal unloading &lt;a href=&#34;http://geology.gsapubs.org/content/39/6/551&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;groundwater mass removal&lt;/a&gt; process. This finding is quite exciting, hitting the media and apparently causing lot of discussion. However, I regret to see some news reports highlighting the word &amp;ldquo;caused&amp;rdquo;, something we didn&amp;rsquo;t say nor endorse in our study. The long-term tectonic stresses accumulated by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.agu.org/pubs/crossref/2004/2002JB002359.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alhama de Murcia Fault&lt;/a&gt; were much larger (0.5-2 MPa) than the simulated stress change due to the unloading process (0.01 MPa). So, it is incorrect to say that the groundwater extraction caused the event. The Alhama de Murcia fault was late in its earthquake cycle, something that perhaps could helped to increase its susceptibility to external forcing. But, our data modelling suggests correlation and therefore we proposed that the unloading stress changes were sufficient to control the way in which the tectonic stress released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that in the future, we could find other examples of such relationship, as it could have profound implications. In that regard, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gps.caltech.edu/~avouac/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;J.-P. Avouac&lt;/a&gt; commented our paper and expose possible future implications of our discovery &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/ngeo/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/ngeo1609.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2010: Shallow flank deformation at Cumbre Vieja volcano (Canary Islands): Implications on the stability of steep-sided volcano flanks at oceanic islands</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/publication/2010/2010-09-01_gonzalezetal_epsl_lapalmainsar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/publication/2010/2010-09-01_gonzalezetal_epsl_lapalmainsar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2010: Modelling deformation occurring in the city of Auckland, New Zealand mapped by the Differential Synthetic Aperture Radar</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/publication/2010/2010-08-25_samsonovetal_jgr_auckland/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/publication/2010/2010-08-25_samsonovetal_jgr_auckland/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
