<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peoples on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</title>
    <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Peoples on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2020 Pablo J. González</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 12:58:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Dr Pablo J Gonzalez</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/pablojgonzalez/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/pablojgonzalez/</guid>
      <description>I grew up in Tenerife loving seawater and mountain views.
At some point, I was told that Teide was a volcano. Few solar revolutions later, a high-school geology teacher inspired me to spend more time looking at rocks. So I did, and at 18, I left Tenerife to Granada and I met more inspiring teachers. There, they call them, professors (thanks Juan Ignacio Soto and Jose Morales). Before graduate, I had a great summer at a Mexican volcano and a full year in Germany (thanks Janet).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Past members</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/pastmembers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/pastmembers/</guid>
      <description>Postdoc researchers  Dr Lidong Bie (COMET Postdoctoral researcher), working on earthquake source processes combining seismology and geodesy.  PhD and MPhil students  Dr Guadalupe Brú (PhD 2018), research on monitoring landslides. Currently at TomTom.com. Currently a science data analyst at Tom Tom Spain. Mr. Teo Nagy (MSc 2018), MPhil Thesis: Automatic glacier displacement maps using Sentinel-2 satellite images. Currently a data analyst at Norwegian Polar Institute. Mr. Jorge Vargas Rivera (MSc Petroleum Geology student, 2016), Induced seismicity at depleting gas reservoirs  Undergraduate students  Ms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visitors</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/visitors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/visitors/</guid>
      <description> Visitors  Ms Sara Rodríguez Molina, PhD Student @ IGEO-CSIC, Madrid (May-June 2017), planned work on time-dependent volcano deformation models  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work with us</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/workwithus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 12:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/people/workwithus/</guid>
      <description>Work with us The University of Liverpool with the Earth, Ocean and Ecological Sciences has a prestigious PhD program in Earth Sciences, all the information on the programme and the requirements to enter are here
If you are already graduated from a MSc or BSc degree in some discipline in Earth Sciences, I can help you to fund your PhD studies using one of the following funding options: 1. Usually, I offer PhD projects for the Liverpool-Manchester Doctoral Training Programme.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>