<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</title>
    <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2020 Pablo J. González</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Observando los volcanoes desde el espacio</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20140712_observandovolcanoesdesdeelespacio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20140712_observandovolcanoesdesdeelespacio/</guid>
      <description>Con una cotidianidad pasmosa nos hemos llegado a acostumbrar a mirar el televisor cada día después de las noticias, y ver una perpectiva, inusual, de otro mundo, uno que nunca hemos observado desde ese punto de vista, pero que sin embargo reconocemos con facilidad. Somos capaces de identificar sin dificultad las líneas continentales, las masas de agua y, el objetivo de esa representación en cámara, la evolución de las nubes, y por ende, del vapor de agua listo para descargar sobre nuestras cabezas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3D-DEF code and manual/tutorial (.pdf)</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130517_3defcode/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130517_3defcode/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I encountered a ground deformation problem where the slip along a particular fault seems not partitioned (distributed) as usual. Most of the elastic dislocation codes assume that slip partitions about half of the slip on one side block (hangingwall) and the other half along the other block (footwall), e.g., the popular Okada codes. These codes will not work when slip occurs only due to the motion of one block. This is basically the problem I want to study, for this you need more advance and flexible programs, one of those is 3D-DEF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carta Abierta al IGN: Política de acceso a datos científicos</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130401_cartaabiertaign/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130401_cartaabiertaign/</guid>
      <description>Estimado Sr./Sra.,
Wikimedia Wikimedia
Me dirijo a Ud. para solicitar que hagan pública su política de acceso a datos científicos generados por el Insituto Geográfico Nacional de España (IGN).
Creo que es de interés público, y en particular de aquellos científicos españoles e internacionales interesados en procesos geológicos y geofísicos ocurridos en el territorio español y sus proximidades, saber cuando, bajo qué condiciones, detalles técnicos de adquisición y en qué formato se puede acceder a todos los datos de carácter científico recabados por el IGN.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hawai&#39;i 2012 a trip to live geohazards: Earthquake, Tsunami, and Volcanoes</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121104_hawaii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121104_hawaii/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I have visited the Maui and Big Island in Hawai’i. I must admit I haven’t had the time to visit Maui properly due to a busy conference schedule ACES2012, so I hope to have another chance to explore the plenty nice rain-forests and waterfalls (Road to Hana), the Haleakala volcano, or just surfing the eastern coast outer reefs (my other passion in life).
However, as I landed into the Big Island, my first passion in life the natural hazards become so intense that I don’t regret to pass the opportunity to surf in Hawai’i (something that certainly sounds very cool to my folks back in the Canary Islands).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2011 Lorca earthquake: groundwater unloading of the crust</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121019_lorca/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20121019_lorca/</guid>
      <description>As recent as Monday, a group of colleagues and myself published a paper in Nature Geoscience, showing proof of a positive correlation between the slip distribution occurred during the 2011 Lorca earthquake and the mid-term (50-years) stress changes due to a crustal unloading groundwater mass removal process. This finding is quite exciting, hitting the media and apparently causing lot of discussion. However, I regret to see some news reports highlighting the word &amp;ldquo;caused&amp;rdquo;, something we didn&amp;rsquo;t say nor endorse in our study.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>