<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Earthquake on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</title>
    <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/tags/earthquake/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Earthquake on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2020 Pablo J. González</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/tags/earthquake/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>3D-DEF code and manual/tutorial (.pdf)</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130517_3defcode/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130517_3defcode/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I encountered a ground deformation problem where the slip along a particular fault seems not partitioned (distributed) as usual. Most of the elastic dislocation codes assume that slip partitions about half of the slip on one side block (hangingwall) and the other half along the other block (footwall), e.g., the popular Okada codes. These codes will not work when slip occurs only due to the motion of one block. This is basically the problem I want to study, for this you need more advance and flexible programs, one of those is 3D-DEF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Carta Abierta al IGN: Política de acceso a datos científicos</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130401_cartaabiertaign/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130401_cartaabiertaign/</guid>
      <description>Estimado Sr./Sra.,
Wikimedia Wikimedia
Me dirijo a Ud. para solicitar que hagan pública su política de acceso a datos científicos generados por el Insituto Geográfico Nacional de España (IGN).
Creo que es de interés público, y en particular de aquellos científicos españoles e internacionales interesados en procesos geológicos y geofísicos ocurridos en el territorio español y sus proximidades, saber cuando, bajo qué condiciones, detalles técnicos de adquisición y en qué formato se puede acceder a todos los datos de carácter científico recabados por el IGN.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>