<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Deformation on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</title>
    <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/tags/deformation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Deformation on Volcano and Fault Mechanics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2020 Pablo J. González</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/tags/deformation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Observando los volcanoes desde el espacio</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20140712_observandovolcanoesdesdeelespacio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20140712_observandovolcanoesdesdeelespacio/</guid>
      <description>Con una cotidianidad pasmosa nos hemos llegado a acostumbrar a mirar el televisor cada día después de las noticias, y ver una perpectiva, inusual, de otro mundo, uno que nunca hemos observado desde ese punto de vista, pero que sin embargo reconocemos con facilidad. Somos capaces de identificar sin dificultad las líneas continentales, las masas de agua y, el objetivo de esa representación en cámara, la evolución de las nubes, y por ende, del vapor de agua listo para descargar sobre nuestras cabezas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3D-DEF code and manual/tutorial (.pdf)</title>
      <link>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130517_3defcode/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://pablojgonzalez.github.io/post/20130517_3defcode/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I encountered a ground deformation problem where the slip along a particular fault seems not partitioned (distributed) as usual. Most of the elastic dislocation codes assume that slip partitions about half of the slip on one side block (hangingwall) and the other half along the other block (footwall), e.g., the popular Okada codes. These codes will not work when slip occurs only due to the motion of one block. This is basically the problem I want to study, for this you need more advance and flexible programs, one of those is 3D-DEF.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>